# Akarsh Balasubramanyam

914 #1 South Oakley Boulevard, Chicago, Illinois - 60612, United States of America

Email: abalas26@uic.edu GitHub: https://www.github.com/Akarsh-B Phone: +1 (773)-744-4763

### **SUMMARY**

A Computer Science Graduate student with research interests in Data Science and Machine Learning. Interested in pursuing career in Software Development or Data Science fields. Experience in Data Extraction and Predictive Analytics for actionable insights.

#### **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATION**

## Master of Science in Computer Science - GPA: 4.0/4.0

Aug 2019-May 2021

University of Illinois at Chicago, Illinois

Relevant Courses: Computer Algorithms, Introduction to Data Science, Introduction to Machine Learning, Neural Networks, Information Retrieval, Deep Learning for NLP, Advanced Data Mining

### Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science - GPA: 79.56%

Aug 2013-June 2017

BMS Institute of Technology and Management, Affiliated to Visvesvaraya Technological University.

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Programming Language C, C++, Python, JavaScript, R
- Tools and Frameworks: Git, SVN, Node.js, Angular9, TestCafe, Docker, Informatica PowerCenter (ETL), Google Cloud
- Database: Oracle SQL, MYSQL, PostgreSQL and MongoDB
- Data Analysis: Numpy, Pandas, Tensorflow, Keras, Scipy, Scikit-Learn, NLTK, Spacy, Seaborn, Bokeh, Tableau, Vis.js
- Machine Learning Models: Regression, SVM, Decision Trees, Random Forest, Classification, Clustering, Neural Nets.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Intern, Software Development- Ensono, LP, Downers Grove, Illinois

June 2019 - Ongoing

- Used Angular9 as a framework to develop Single Page Application (Agile In A Box) to access and display data from JIRA
- Visualized JIRA stories and its dependencies using Vis.js and used Bitbucket for version control
- Worked with Jasmine/Karma and TestCafe for Unit and End-to-End Testing

## Software Engineer 1 - Dell Technologies, Bengaluru, India

July 2017 - July 2019

- Analyze and Maintained Customer Data in the Production Environment by resolving Data and Hierarchy issues that would occur on a daily basis
- Designed and Developed mappings and transformations using Informatica PowerCenter to extract data from multiple sources and perform Data Warehousing at a Central MDM repository
- Developed an Account Dashboard a tool encompassing operational KPI's and SLA's for Accounts transactions using ETL and SQL technologies
- Took an initiative to lead and manage a Level-2 team and trained them to support the Master Data Management application

#### Under-Graduate Intern - Bharath Sanchar Nigam Limited, Bengaluru, India

Jan 2016 – May 2016

- · Received training about networking and switching devices and the wireless communication routing at BSNL
- Developed a tool that supports automated Broadband provision and modification using Python and Shell scripts

#### **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

## **Automatic Text Summarization and Ranking of email corpus**

Feb 2020 - May 2020

• Ranking of email corpus using Information Retrieval and NLP techniques based on frequently used keywords that describe the priority of the emails (ASAP, Immediate, Critical) and Summarize them using Text Rank algorithm.

## **Analysis of Crime Data of City of Chicago**

Oct 2019 - Dec 2019

• Analyze and predict the type of crime that may occur in the city of Chicago and dictate the possibility of criminal being arrested. Achieved an 86% accuracy predicting the criminal being arrested and 60% accuracy for the type of crime

## **Tag Prediction for Stack Overflow Questions**

Oct 2019 - Dec 2019

 Predict Tags for the question posted on Stack Overflow and compare Accuracy metrics using different Machine Learning models like Multinomial Bayes, Logistic Regression and Support Vector Machines

## **Intrusion Detection using Ad-hoc Communication Networks**

Jan 2017 – June 2017

 A cost-effective, autonomous, two-level security Robots designed using Raspberry Pi and Arduino with Radio Frequency Identification and Facial Recognition